Okay, so anyway, so today's דף daf *daf* is ו *vav*, so
ערכין Erchin. *Arachin* ו *vav*, and we pick up at six and
we pick up on the bottom of ה *he* עמוד ב *amud
bet*. So bottom of ה *he* עמוד ב *amud bet*, we're discussing
the question about non-Jews. Are they in the category of ערך erech,
*erech*? Can they obligate themselves as an ערך erech, *erech*? Can they
be an object of an ערך erech. *erech*? And the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says that it was inclined to rule that if they should
be excluded, it should be from giving an ערך erech, *erech* because
of this story and this verse in עזרא Ezra? *Ezra* where they
did not want the non-Jews to contribute at the beginning of the
building of the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash, *Beit HaMikdash* because they were
concerned that it would undermine it as a Jewish enterprise. So as
תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* points out, this does not mean that we should
completely exclude them. The משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says נודרין *nodrin*, they can
give a נדר neder, *neder*, but if there's going to be an
exclusion within ערכין Erchin? *erchin*, we would more be inclined towards this
type of an exclusion. So let's see now as the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* continues. גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
רבי יהודה *Rebbe
Yehuda*, it is six lines from the bottom, three words in on
ה *he* עמוד ב *amud bet*. רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*, רבי יהודה
האי לא lo, לכם ולנו מאי עביד ליה *Rebbe Yehuda Hai lo
lachem velanu mai avid lei*. Since רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says that
a non-Jew can be מעריך *maarich*, what does he do with this
verse in עזרא נחמיה Ezra Nechemia. *Ezra Nechemia* that they did not
want the non-Jews to be participating? So אמר רב חסדא אמר רב
אבימי וערכו נגנז *Amar Rav Chisda Amar Rav Avimi Ve'erko nignaz*. Ah,
because what he would say is I agree that you should not
accept their contributions. Again, this can be read very broadly, but it's
applied here specifically to ערכין Erchin. *erchin*. But if they give an
ערך erech? *erech*, that actually that is effective. So if they say
I will give an ערך erech, *erech* and they
set aside the money, it becomes sanctified. Now as a policy matter,
we're not going to use it, but it became sanctified. So what
do you do with it? נגנז *Nignaz*? No, no, non-Jews. Wait, what?
Sussam and Drozunus was just the analogy. Just
non, well here it means first of all עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim
*Ovei Kochavim* in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is almost always a later
self-censorship and the original text would be גוי goy *goy* or נוכרי
*nochri*. So it's sometimes by context it only means idolaters, but here
the sense is that it means all non-Jews. Just a question of
undermining the sense of it as a Jewish enterprise, the building of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*. Now we're going to see,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s going to continue today to limit and qualify,
and as I said already, תוספות Tosafot *Tosafot* points out that they
are, they can give a נדר neder *neder*. So this is just
because there are these concerns, you know, if the תורה *Torah*'s going
to make some, draw some lines by ערכין erchin. *erchin*, we will
focus on this. But it's not understood to be a complete across-the-board.
Nevertheless, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here says that even רבי יהודה *Rebbe
Yehuda* who says that they make an ערך erech, *erech* and it
gets sanctified when they set aside the money would agree that the
policy is you shouldn't accept it. So what do you do with
it? You bury it. So that's an interesting way of importing that
kind of idea within רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*. And again, it is
a waste, and again, you know, it's only by ערכין *erchin* we
say this, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* says נודרין *nodrin*. Let's take a
look as the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues. אלא מעתה לא ימעלו בו
*Ela meata lo yimalu bo*, if that's really true that you bury
it, then if it's never going to be used, there shouldn't be
מעילה *meila*. Because basically the principle is if something is sanctified but
it does not have the ability to ever be used, there's no
prohibition of מעילה *meila*. And we are going to see that רבי
יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* says there is מעילה *meila* with the ערך erech
*erech* of that non-Jews make to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit
HaMikdash*. דתנן *Ditnan*,
and here's how I'll prove to you there shouldn't be מעילה *meila*.
Because we have in a משנה Mishnah. *Mishnah* חמש חטאות מתות *Chamesh
chatatot metot*, the five חטאות *chatatot* that have to be let die,
we've come across those before. ומעות ילכו לים המלח *Umotei yelchu le'yam
hamelach* or money that for some reason is sanctified but cannot be
used and has to be thrown into the Dead Sea. Again, we're
not going to go into what puts something in that category, but
there are some things that are sanctified that cannot in any way
be benefited from and used. The הלכה *halakha* is לא נהנין *lo
nehenin*, you're not rabbinically allowed to derive benefit ולא מועלין *velo moalin*,
but you do not transgress מעילה *meila* since it is not ultimately
able to be used by the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*.
So if that were true that the ערך erech *erech* would have
to be buried according to רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*, it wouldn't have
מעילה *meila*. Then אלא מה תניא *Alama tanya* why do we teach
a ברייתא braita. *braita* גבי קדשי Kodshei, עובדי כוכבים ovdei kochavim *gabei
kodshei ovei kochavim* by things that they sanctified? במה דברים אמורים *Bameh
devarim amurim*, when is it true that there's no מעילה *meila* by
something a non-Jew sanctified? בקדשי מזבח *Bekodshei Mizbeach*, if it's a sacrifice.
אבל בקדשי בדק הבית Bedek HaBayit. מועלין בו *Aval bekodshei bedek habayit
moalin bo*, if they sanctify something to the temple there is מעילה
*meila*. So according to you, there shouldn't be מעילה *meila* if you
say that it has to be buried. And this has to be
רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda* because according to רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* they
can't even sanctify it. So it says they did sanctify it, which
is רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*, and it says there's מעילה *meila*. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says you know what, you're right. אלא אמר
רבא Rava. *Ela amar Rava*, רבא *Rava* says you're right. According to
רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*, they can give an ערך erech *erech*, they
can sanctify it, and you would use it, which is obviously the
simple sense of רבי יהודה *Rebbe Yehuda*. So what does he do
with that story in עזרא *Ezra*? So he says משום רפיון ידיים
הוא *Mishum rifyon yadayim hu*, that story was very unique to those
circumstances. We don't learn out. general policy. And that was a specific
concern that it would weaken their hands, it would undermine the enterprise.
דכתיב ויהי עם הארץ מרפים ידי עם יהודה מבהלים אותם לבנות. That
the people of the land, the, you know, the inhabitants of the
land of Judea that were the non-Jews, were trying to weaken the
hands of the Jews that were building the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash
the second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash? So there's this real concern about
the success of the enterprise. It was very vulnerable and therefore we
they had to make very much be sensitive and protective. So those
that wanted to contribute, there was a concern that they had ulterior
motives and they would use it as a way to manipulate and
to undermine their involvement and that was a very
specific unique circumstances. We don't make general policy based on that. Okay,
so that becomes now, that now we sort of have like this
big general question, do we learn out policy from this one story
in עזרא? But again, and the גמרא Gemara will continue with that
question,
the תוספות Tosafot. points out, you know, and I keep, this is
the fifth time I've said this,
the גמרא Gemara, makes it sound like this is a general policy.
But in the end we're applying it only to ערכין. The משנה
mishna says that נדר, neder, if you just did it in a
different way by making a vow rather than making an ערך, erech,
we would accept it. So it's worth realizing that that's true even
according to the one that says we do learn out some policy
from this story. So now with that in
mind, a question like, what's so specific about ערכין? You know?
Right. So that's what תוספות Tosafos says. It's really nothing specific about
ערכין. But that given that we have to limit something and given
that we see concerns about this, that if we're going to limit
it, we'll limit it in this way. But right, but if that
were true, right, but if that were true, then you would not
never find it translated into more general policy. And that's going to
be challenged just by the simple sense of the גמרא Gemara we
just read and also by what we're going to see now at
the top of ו עמוד א. vav amud aleph. So let's take
a look at the top of ו עמוד א. vav amud aleph.
Okay, so, now today's דף ו עמוד א, vav amud aleph, תני
חדא. tani chada. We taught one ברייתא. braita עובדי כוכבים שנדרו, shenadru,
notice this is now a נדבה, nedavah, נדר neder, not ערכין. So
according to our משנה or whatever, there should be no problem with
it. But now we're going to still see that some of those
policy concerns are being brought in. Okay, so עובדי כוכבים שנדרו shenadru
gave a gift, נדבה לבדק הבית nedavah le-vedek ha-bayit to the temple
treasury, מקבלין מהן, mekablin mehen, you accept it. Why not? We'll accept
gifts from anyone. ותני אידך, ve-tanya idach, contributions are always accepted. Another
ברייתא braisa says אין מקבלין. ein mekablin. Nope, you don't accept their
contribution. So how do you reconcile this? So אמר רבי אילא אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Ila amar Rabbi Yochanan, לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. הא בתחילה הא בסוף. ha bi-techilah ha be-sof. Depends
whether it's at the beginning or the end. There's a little ambiguity
what this means, but the simple explanation is that it means are
they making a contribution when you're sort of laying the foundation at
the very at the very beginning of the process or, no, basically
you've raised most of the money, you're you're now raising some extra
funds for some, you know, you need to do some improvements or
you need to finally cap off the campaign. That makes a big
difference. And how do we know this again? This is the build
this and this is the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The גמרא Gemara
is not, is not identifying this to questions about synagogues or whatever,
this is in the context of בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash And this
is what we learned directly from עזרא נחמיה. Ezra Nechemia. When you're
starting the process, you've got to make sure that that is, you
know, established firmly that as the Jewish people we're taking responsibility for
it, that we are sort of setting, you know, the agenda and
so on. Once we're well on the way and there's no question
who's owning the process and that we're invested and that it's getting
done, then you can accept more outside contributions. Okay, and I think
you can understand the logic of that in terms of really, you
know, what that would mean in terms of who is really investing
and owning it and who is it who's identified with it and
so on. So once the foundation is laid, later in the process,
we can accept more outside contributions.
But you're seeing it, if you wanted to be more restrictive, it
depends if it's the beginning of the year or the end of
the year. Beginning of the year, you know, we're we're, you know,
you really want like because every year you probably need stuff for
בדק הבית. What's the beginning of the building of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash versus the end? And towards the end of the year,
you kind of know what your funds are if you have a
surplus and they want to give a little extra and you may
say, okay, I'll accept it.
Okay, but that's not what fine, so that's פירש peirush of Michael,
but it's not רש"י Rashi or תוספות. Tosafos So anyway, so let's
keep on going. And and you know and again the the רש"י's
Rashi explanation is directly sort of reflecting the story in עזרא נחמיה.
Let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says דאמר רבי אבא de-amar
Rabbi Abba לא קשיא lo kashya הא בתחילה הא בסוף. ha bi-techilah
ha be-sof. דאמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rabbi Assi amar
Rabbi Yochanan, בתחילה, bi-techilah, if they want to donate in the beginning
of the process, אפילו מים ומלח אין מקבלין. afilu mayim u-melach ein
mekablin. Even the most basic things, even if they want to just
salt and water, which obviously probably not going to actually put into
the construction. Maybe it's paying, maybe it's giving the workers some of
their food, paying some fees, but no, the beginning we have to
be established totally in control by the people, their investment and so
on, not by outside contributions. Okay, so that's at the beginning. לבסוף
le-vasof at the end, now we're we are going to add some
restrictions at the end. דבר המסוים אין מקבלין דבר שאינו מסוים מקבלין.
Davar ha-mesuyam ein mekablin davar she-eino mesuyam mekablin.
Something identified and specific you do not accept. Something generic you do
accept. Meaning funds, fine, it gets absorbed into all the other funds.
Not a problem. But if they want to donate a specific item
like they want to donate the ארון קודש, Aron Kodesh, right, and
the ארון קודש Aron Kodesh is donated by Kris Kristofferson or something
like that, so that would be seen as inappropriate that there would
be a specific item identified as the, you know, as the donation
from the outside, the donation from the non-Jews. This is a Jewish
temple, and therefore, you know, a generic donation is fine, but not
as a specific. היכי דמי דבר מסויים? Heychi dami dvar misuyam? What
would be an example of
דבר מסויים? dvar misuyam? אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, כגון אמה
כליא עורב, kigon ama khalya oreiv, the and the אמה ama the
that was to scare away the ravens. Basically, you know, you had
these open-air altar with all this meat burning on it, it would
attract the birds. So what they did was they basically on the
roof they made spikes on the roof, you know, and they basically
I should say it would be like a piece of metal, an
אמה ama by an אמה, ama, you know they have like multiple
tiles like this, there's different interpretations what it would look like. Anyway,
filled with high spikes, so if any birds tried to come close,
you know, they would get scared away. Others say that it might
have even been more like a scarecrow or something. Anyway, so it
gives that as an example. Why does it give that as an
example? I imagine it gives that as an example to say even
if that's not something that's so like חשוב, chashuv, you know, ah,
it's not like the ארון קודש. Aron Kodesh. When I gave you
the example, I gave you like an extreme, an ארון קודש. Aron
Kodesh. But you might think something a little more trivial, you know,
like the thing for scaring away the birds, who cares? Right, but
says no, anything that is specific we want we you know, if
it's a Jewish temple, it's got to be identified as Jewish. So
if it's a generic contribution, that's okay.
What if they wanted to dedicate one of the stones? They could,
or is that not? Because it is a stone. What? If they
wanted to dedicate a stone to like build the בית המקדש? Beit
Hamikdash? Is that something specific because it's just a stone? Or not,
because you can't really...
If it's a specific stone, you you know, and oh I see,
they just handed you a stone and you were going to build
it in and you wouldn't know where that particular... Presumably that would
be okay. Anyway, רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom adds that it's not only
that it would be named by it and remembered, you know, and
sort of given that outside identification, but also if it's something specific,
you know, and this will tie into the next line, you don't
want him coming later and saying 'I want to take it back.'
Right, so therefore, so that's why you don't want something specific. And
again we're concerned that because it's coming from outside, not the people
whose temple it actually is, that there's more of that concern that
you know, that type of claim might be made.
So if you were going to donate to a temple you're not
going to get it back.
Right, but you don't want the person making that claim and making
trouble. What were you always saying though? No plaques. No plaques. No
plaques for the contributions from the non-Jews. Right. All right. So now
the גמרא Gemara says, okay, so we're going to... don't worry, the
obvious parallel to this and synagogues is going to continue, so don't
worry. Anyway, so מתיב רב יוסף, masiv Rav Yosef, so רב יוסף
Rav Yosef asked on this, ואיגרת אל אסף שומר הפרדס, v'igeres el
Asaf shomeir hapardeis, there was a letter from the king to
אסף Asaf who watched the garden אשר למלך asher lamelech that was
the king's garden, to basically tell him to contribute, you know, wood
to the building of the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash, So here you
see they're contributing to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash? and it's at
the beginning of the process. Now תוספות says, 'I don't understand, the
whole בית המקדש beit hamikdash. was under Cyrus's directive and with his
support.' So תוספות says, 'fine, that was כורש, Koresh, that was in
the פסוק posuk ישעיהו Yeshayahu already prophesied about כורש, Koresh, that was
that was an exception.' But here the person making... although he was
commanded by the king, the person making the contribution was somebody else,
was not directly כורש. Koresh. And therefore, how do we accept those
types of contributions? So אמר ליה אביי, Amar leih Abaye, so אביי
Abaye said, שאני מלכותא דלא הדרא בה. shani malchusa d'lo hadra beih.
Ah, when it's done by the directive of the king, they're not
going to take it back. דאמר אמר שמואל, d'amar amar Shmuel, for
שמואל Shmuel said, אי אמר מלכותא עקרנא טורא עקר טורא ולא הדרא
בה, i amar malchusa akarna tura, akar tura v'lo hadra beih, if
the king says 'I'll uproot the
mountains,' they will find a way to uproot the mountains and they
won't reverse themselves.
Exactly, exactly, just like in the מגילה Megillah by פורים.
Purim. Exactly, exactly, just like in the מגילה Megillah by פורים. Purim.
So number one, it means that they have the power to do
what they say. And number two, it means that for their reputation
presumably they are going to follow through with what they say. It's
interesting that שמואל Shmuel in general, we know, had a very positive
attitude towards the secular government. שמואל Shmuel is the one that said
דינא דמלכותא דינא, dina d'malchusa dina, that the rule of the government
is the rule. שמואל Shmuel was very close to שבור מלכא, Shvor
Malka, you know, to the secular king, to the Persian government. Anyway,
so this is a statement of שמואל. Shmuel. Now what does it
have to do with reversing? Presumably the concern at the beginning is
just that they're going to, you know, be have an investment at
the at the beginning and they'll sort of be seen as partners
and you want it to be, you know, Jewish and you don't
want it to, you know, and
the full sense of ownership and control is Jewish. So it's not
so clear. רש״י Rashi indicates that maybe it really means about a
question about how sincere is what they are doing. Like when the
question about will they go back on it, it means like are
they going to try to claim 'I want my money back'? Are
they going to try to make problems? Are they going to try
to make... undermine, so it's not so much about whether they actually
reverse themselves as about whether it's like is it a sincere and
complete donation or is it going to lead to troubles down the
way? You know, and so A, was it דווקא davka with an
intent to undermine, or even not an intent? And if you want
to focus specifically on the idea of going back, are they going
to say, let's say it's just out of self-interest, are they going
to say, I changed my mind, give me back my money? Right?
That happens sometimes, right? That people are invested in a project, people
make donations, certainly people sometimes don't fulfill their vows, but sometimes actually
say, I don't like the way this is going, give me back
my money. So if that, that's the concern, not that they'll sort
of, you know, sort of try to mess it up for the
sake of messing it up, but just a concern that they might
back out. So therefore, that's not a concern when it comes to
if the king is actually behind it, we're not going to be
concerned about that.
Even if he was the
one who destroyed the בית המקדש? beit hamikdash? Well, not כורש. Coresh.
Yeah, but apparently if they're behind it and they're invested in it,
not, anyway, so that's interesting because it frames the concern differently. It's
not so much of a concern that they're going to try to
manipulate the process, right? Then if anything you could say the government,
maybe you have more of a concern if the government's invested they're
going to try to manipulate. But now at least the way the
גמרא Gemara allows, explains that we allow for the government to be
there in the beginning, is more of a concern that they're going
to make trouble because they're going to want to back out and
that's going to lead to trouble.
Government can manipulate the situation regardless.
That's an interesting
point.
That's an interesting point.
That's an interesting point. If the government wants to manipulate, it doesn't
have to be through contribution. That's a good point. That's a good
point.
Okay, so let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara, continues.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, עובד כוכבים
שהפריש תרומה מכריו, Oveid kochavim shehefrish terumah mikiryav, a non-Jew separates תרומה
terumah from his own grain, from his own pile of grain. He
grew grain in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. There's a question whether non-Jewish
ownership of land in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael removes its קדושה, kedusha,
obviously very relevant for selling land to a non-Jew for the שמיטה
Shemita year. But this is following the opinion that it does not.
So a non-Jew grew grain in his own land, and normally the
question is, okay, so if I buy the grain, I have to
separate תרומה terumah and מעשר. ma'aser. But we're not talking about that.
We're talking about that he is separating תרומה terumah and מעשר. ma'aser.
We've never heard about that before. But if the grain actually has
sanctity of תרומה terumah and מעשר, ma'aser, what if he separated it?
Does it take effect? If he can make a vow and that
vow can actually sanctify, not only obligate him, but sanctify objects for
the Temple, maybe he also, he can actually separate תרומה terumah and
מעשר ma'aser of his own grain. So let's take a look. עובד
כוכבים שהפריש תרומה מכריו, Oveid kochavim shehefrish terumah mikiryav, he separates תרומה
terumah from his own grain. בודקין אותו, Bodkin oto, you have a,
you have an interview with him. You check out what he was
thinking. אם בדעת ישראל הפרישה, Im bedaat Yisrael hifrishah, if he's doing
it with the Jewish mindset. What does that mean with a Jewish
mindset? Either it means that, oh, I did it because my friend,
the Jew, told me that it would be a good idea that
I should do it. Okay, that's one explanation, by the direction of
a Jew. Or maybe more simply, what it means, רש״י Rashi gives
both explanations, that it means, I wanted it to work like it
works for the Jews. You know, that was what he was thinking.
I see Jews do it, I want it to be like the
Jews do it. Okay, if that's his intention, so he wants it
to be תרומה terumah even if he doesn't know the specifics, then
תינתן לכהן, tinaten lekohen, then it's תרומה, terumah, give it to a
כהן. kohen. So a non-Jew, if the grain has קדושה, kedusha, it's
his own grain, he can actually make תרומה. terumah. ואם לאו, Ve’im
lav, one minute, if that wasn't what he was thinking, then טעונה
גניזה, teuna genizah, then we have to bury. Why? חיישינן שמא
בלבו לשמים, Chayshinan shema belibo lashamayim,
maybe when he said תרומה, terumah, you know the Torah uses the
word תרומה terumah in different ways. תרומה Terumah is what you give
from the grain, but when they begin building the בית המקדש, beit
hamikdash what is the, what's the name of the פרשה parsha where
they build the בית המקדש? Beis HaMikdash, תרומה. Terumah. זאת התרומה, Zos
haterumah,
it's a gift. So maybe what he meant was, I want to
give it as a gift to the Temple. And if that's true,
then it's, has sanctified with the קדושה kedusha of the Temple. So
therefore since we don't know which it is, and you can't use
it, you can't just play it safe, because if you use it
for the Temple, maybe it's תרומה. terumah. You can't use תרומה terumah
that way. Right now you wonder why doesn't the Temple take it
and feed it to the כהנים? kohanim? But if it's, then it's
קדשי בדק הבית, kodshei bedek habayis, כהנים kohanim can't eat קדשי בדק
הבית. kodshei bedek habayis. So you're like a little bit stuck. You
can't like find a way to use it either way, so you
have to bury it.
Let it like become טמא tamei or something like that?
No, you can't be allowed תרומה terumah to become טמא. tamei.
No, just make it, you know, sort of like.
No, even to allow בגרם be-geram תרומה terumah is an issue. טומאה
Tuma is an issue. So anyway, because you don't know whether it's
real תרומה terumah or whether it's sanctified for the Temple treasury, what
does he mean by the word תרומה? terumah? You have to, you
can't do anything, you have to bury it. Yes, David, you had
a question.
Right,
so that's a good point. So there is a whole question of
how we think about אינו מצווה ועושה, eino metzuve ve'oseh, somebody who's
not commanded and does. Do we think that that person, that מצווה
mitzvah acts of such a person are completely meaningless? Or do we
think that they are מצווה mitzvah acts, but they are not on
the same level as being commanded? It might depend on who we're
talking about. Let's say, you know, let's say positive מצוות mitzvos that
women are exempt from. The normal assumption is there... that they actually
when they do it, they do a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* act. It's
not like it's meaningless, and actually they make a ברכה *bracha*, at
least אשכנזים *Ashkenazim*. But what let's say a non-Jew were to take
a לולב *lulav* on סוכות *Sukkot*, we would normally assume that that
was a meaningless act. Not like it was a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*
act. The רמב"ם Rambam *Rambam* interestingly, though, says that even for non-Jews
who do מצוות *mitzvot*, it's
they are doing a מצוה *mitzvah* act, it's just not at the
same level. But anyway, this is not a question about whether they
get merit for doing the מצוה *mitzvah*. We're not talking about their
checkpoints or brownie points. We're talking about whether it's effective to, right.
So, right, right. So that's part of what this חידוש chiddush *chiddush*
is. But I wouldn't frame it as a מצוה *mitzvah*, like all
of what this משנה *Mishnah* has introduced is you're right, this is
part of a larger discussion of what types of things that non-Jews
do are recognized as מצוות *mitzvot* or recognized as sort of like,
you know, sort of religiously
meaningful within a Jewish context. And certainly one major area is this:
they can bring קרבנות *korbanot*. If they bring קרבנות *korbanot*, it means
they sanctify the animal. So they so this is sort of part
of whether we call it a מצוה *mitzvah* or not is not
really relevant, but part of recognizing that non-Jews can create sanctity that
has meaning within a Jewish context. They can sanctify קרבנות *korbanot*, they
can sanctify objects to the temple treasury. Once we're saying they can
give to the temple in either ways, it's not crazy to say
that they can make תרומה terumah *terumah*, especially if we're saying that
the קדושה kedusha *kedusha* is already inherent in the grain, and they're
just in a way actualizing that by separating it, right? So you
are correct to point that out, that it's a big חידוש chiddush
*chiddush* here because you would have thought somebody outside of the system
can't create these קדושות *kedushot*. But we are saying that a non-Jew
can, but it's not necessarily the same as a question as whether
it's a מצוה *mitzvah*. Yes, Rivka?
Yes, I have two questions.
First, to start
delving into people's motives is very difficult. It's you're setting up almost
an inquisition situation to try to determine what somebody's motives are. Their
motives may not even be so completely clear to them.
Okay, but I would say it's not as much motives as intent.
I don't care what motivated you. No, no, no, but it's not
why. It's not why, it's what did you mean? By תרומה terumah
*terumah* did you mean the grain תרומה terumah? *terumah*? Or
did you or were you giving meaning no, you might have been
motivated because you like your friend the Jew, because you want to
look פרום *frum*, it's not the why. It's what were you trying
to do? Were you trying to give this as grain תרומה trumah
*terumah*, or were you trying to give this as a donation to
the temple? It's clarifying intent, it's not trying to identify motive.
But shouldn't we do that throughout, right?
But but even more so by not making a definitive decision. Yes,
we accept it, no, we don't accept it, sometimes it's accepted, sometimes
we bury it. Then you're encouraging more people to give. If there
was a clear decision, no, sorry, this is our policy, we don't
accept, then people would stop donating. But by the rabbis' indecisiveness, they
are opening the door for more such donations that may all be
thrown into ים המלח *Yam Hamelach*.
Okay, but you could also say that if you would accept everything,
you would encourage people to give. This is a middle situation. But
they have to make up
their mind! Right, but I guess what that okay, I hear the
point, but I guess what it shows is that הלכה *Halakha* is
not always made on policy decisions, you know. If they have a
genuine question about what is happening here, then they're not going to
say, well, because it's in policy's best interest to say one thing,
we're going to say it.
If they genuinely feel—I understand. But sometimes הלכה *Halakha* deals with ספק
*safek*, and being in a case of ספק *safek* is often the
worst of both worlds because you're not clear either way. But just
because it puts us in a difficult situation doesn't mean that we're
going to ignore the fact that we have a genuine doubt. But
this will continue. I understand. Hopefully people will therefore learn. You're right,
they might not.
But they don't learn, they won't know why.
Well, if they know that it gets thrown out most of the
time,
then they're going to know. You're not going to say, okay, I'll
take it, I'm going to bury it deep in the earth.
No,
it might be touched.
I don't know.
Okay, if they out if they explicitly say Jewish תרומה trumah *terumah*,
just say Jewish
תרומה trumah *terumah* and you're safe.
Yeah, because if the temple if it were sanctified for temple use,
then they could redeem it, sell it. I mean, it's actually true
that there is a way to do it.
I don't really get why they can't, this stuff that you don't
know if it's sanctified for the temple or if it's תרומה *terumah*.
Because what you could do is you could have a כהן kohen?
*kohen* redeem I mean, why don't you both redeem it and give
it to a כהן *kohen*?
Well, what if he says, I want to give it to the
temple, why are you so unfair?
No, if he says, I want to give it to the temple,
it's fine. But if he says it doesn't say that's a good
point. It says אם לאו *im lav*, he doesn't say explicitly Jewish
תרומה *terumah*. He just says, I don't know what I was thinking,
I said תרומה *terumah*. Right, right. If he I assume that if
he explicitly said a temple donation, that we would interpret it that
way. Okay, so all right, let's keep on going. But it does
seem to me there should be a way out. That why don't
you redeem it on a פרוטה and give the rest to a
כהן? I don't know, there seems to me there might have been
a way out. Anyway, let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara. says
like this.
Okay.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask you on this. עובד כוכבים שנתנדב קורה, Akum
shehitnadev korah, a non-Jew gave a beam for the temple, I understand
you're doing some construction. ושם כתב עליה, VeShem katav aleha, but on
the beam he wrote
להשם, laHashem, okay, י-ה-ו-ה, Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei, so now it looks to show that
he's donating it to the temple. What do you do now? בודקין
אותו, Bodkin oto, you investigate. אם אמר בדעת ישראל הפרשתיה, Im amar
bedaas Yisrael hifrashtiah, I wanted to give it like Jews give normal
donations, so יגוד, yigod, so you take out the place where God's
name is written, because obviously that's like שמות, sheimos, it has קדושת
השם, kedushas Hashem, you don't want to put that in your ceiling,
so that you bury it, וישתמש במותר, veyishtamesh bemoto, use the rest
of the beam. What?
Written by a non-Jew has קדושת השם? kedushas Hashem?
Yeah, so that's interesting.
What is exactly the status of שם השם Shem Hashem written by
a non-Jew? Is this just a question about כבוד kavod or is
this does it have real קדושת השם? kedushas Hashem? It sounds from
this גמרא, Gemara. at least this ברייתא braisa believes that it has
real קדושת השם kedushas Hashem because we'll see it the next line.
Okay, but let me bury it but
put it in the beam, because that's
like a, I guess two things. First of all, that might cause
it to be erased and there's an איסור issur to be מוחק
שם השם. mochek Shem Hashem. Number two, what? Bury it, it's the
natural, it's not your uses, it's I don't know, maybe. Anyway, the
other, but it's, yeah, somehow it seems like it's less respectful to
have something with שם השם Shem Hashem that you're using than גניזה,
genizah, although you're right, eventually it decomposes, it's sort of a way
that saying it's like it's off limits, as opposed to being used.
But what do we say if? Anyway, let's read a few more
sentences, please.
Okay. ואם, Veim, okay, so יגוד, yigod, cut it out וישתמש במותר,
veyishtamesh bemoto, use the rest. ואם לאו, Veim lav, and if he
does not say "as Jews give", טעונה גניזה, teunah genizah, then you
have to bury it. Why? חיישינן שמא בלבו לשמים, Chayshinan shema belibo
lashamayim,
because then we're concerned that he sanctified the whole thing. Now who
cares if he sanctified the whole thing, we're using it in the
temple, right? But by the תרומה you could say we're sort of
stuck, קרבן korban as a, oh maybe that's a burnt, anyway, so
but by the תרומה even there I didn't fully get why we
were stuck because maybe you redeem it. But anyway, here why are
you stuck, just put it in the temple. So רש״י Rashi says,
רש״י Rashi seems to be bothered with this, the רש״י Rashi about
five lines above the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom says, טעונה גניזה, teunah
genizah, I'm sorry not the
טעונה גניזה, teunah genizah, three lines below the רבינו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom
begins לשמים להקדיש להקדש
ובזמן הזה אין לו תקנה. lashamayim lehakdish lehekdesh uvizman hazeh ein lo
takkanah. So we're talking not about the time when there's a temple,
okay? So we're talking about, so notice in this ברייתא Braisa does
not say שנתנדב קורה לבית הבית. shehitnadev korah lebeas habayis. It just
says שנתנדב קורה. shehitnadev korah. So he's actually contributing it to your
שול, shul, we're not talking about the time when there's a temple.
And there there's a concern because if he meant to sanctify it
like real sanctity, like temple treasury sanctity, then there's nothing we can
do with it, right? קדשי,
nowadays if you have things that are sanctified, if you remember what
we learned at the end of בכורות, Bechorot, you have to bury
them, destroy them, there's no, we're concerned you're going to misuse them,
there's nothing to do with them. Okay, so that's the way רש״י
Rashi understands. Okay, so here he's, if there's a possibility he didn't
just want to give it as a donation to the שול, shul,
but he said בדעת ישראל, bedaat Yisrael, however Jews give donations to
their שול shuls that's what I wanted to do. But if he
can't say that, we're concerned he actually sanctified it and non-Jews have
the ability to sanctify nowadays. If it's sanctified we can't do anything
with it. That's the way רש״י Rashi understands. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says, you see, so why is this a question? So
the גמרא Gemara says like this, טעמא
דשם כתב עליה דבעי גניזה, taama deshame katav aleha dibay genizah, the
reason that we are particularly concerned here that it was a real
sanctity was because he wrote God's name on it. That is a
sign that he really might have wanted to sanctify it. הא אין
שם כתב עליה, Ha ein shem katav aleha, if there had not
been God's name, he just came with this beam, לא בעי גניזה,
lo bay genizah, we would not have assumed that he might have
wanted to sanctify it. So why not say the same about the
תרומה? If there's not something blatantly obvious, we're not going to interpret
it as temple sanctity. So the גמרא Gemara says, הוא הדין דאף
על גב דאין שם כתב עליה, hu hadin deaf al gav de-ein
shem katav aleha, no,
if he donates something and he cannot tell us he's doing it
the Jewish way, then we are concerned that his donations might be
temple sanctity and therefore we're stuck. So one minute, one minute, דאף
על גב דאין שם כתב עליה נמי בעי גניזה, deaf al gav
de-ein shem katav aleha nami bay genizah,
you would have to therefore, if it might be temple treasury, you
have to do גניזה. genizah. So why did the example of the
beam say that God's name is written on it? דהא קא משמע
לן, De-hakamosh malan, what it's telling us is the חידוש the other
way. דאף על גב דשם כתב עליה, De-af al gav deshem katav
aleha, even if God's name is written on it, if he tells
us that he meant to donate it the Jewish way and not
sanctify it for the temple, then we're allowed to use it even
if God's name is written on it as long as יגוד וישתמש
במותר, yigod veyishtamesh bemotar, as long as we cut out the God's
name. Therefore it only sanctifies to שם שלא במקומו לאו קדוש, Shem
she-lo bimkomo lav kadosh,
God's name does not sanctify the space beyond where it's written. Okay,
and therefore it only sanctifies the immediate area, only that we have
to cut out. So number one, going back to the question of
why are we cutting this out, does if a non-Jew writes שם
השם shem Hashem does it have קדושה kedusha. or is it just
not to show disrespect? The framing of the ברייתא braisa sounds like
it actually thinks it has קדושה. kedusha, It's just saying it doesn't
sanctify the whole beam, it only sanctifies the immediate area. But the
conclusion of the גמרא Gemara therefore is you cut out God's name,
you don't want to use it, that would be a misuse of
God's name and so on. But in general, if he gives a
donation and we cannot be certain that he meant to do it
like the Jewish way, we have to be concerned that he meant
to actually sanctify it. Now, I could, and then we're stuck. Now,
I would imagine that this is particularly true in the pagan world
where a normal way in which they gave their offerings to the
gods was not necessarily sacrifices, but actually was sanctifying objects, precious objects,
or you know, and actually putting them in the temple. I don't
know if you heard this a few months ago, they found a,
what was it, a Buddhist temple I think, or was it a...
yeah, yeah, was it Buddhist or was it Hindu?
No, it was Buddhist.
Buddhist. Anyway, and that they opened it up and in the treasury
of it they had like bright, billion, literally I think at least
hundreds of millions, I don't know if it was literally billions. Anyway,
of precious gold and whatever, donations that people had given over the
years. But it wasn't to sell and use the proceeds to build.
These were the donations, you know, this is the act of religious
sacrifice was not only with animals. So I assume that we're talking
in the context of the pagan world. In the context of the
pagan world, there's a very serious reason that if he doesn't say
I'm doing it the Jewish way, we think he means to actually
sanctify it to the temple. And then we're stuck.
And as I was trying to say before is,
isn't it or is it not parallel to גוי writes ספר תורה
Sefer Torah with שם השם, shem Hashem, we also put it in
גניזה, gniza, right?
Yes, but I understand, so the question is, so is it because
of קדושה, kedusha is it because of respect, how do you deal
with that? Fine. So yes, this is relevant to that conversation. This
indicates that there's real קדושה to that. Okay, so that is, that
is the principle here but again, I would be curious to know
if פוסקים poskim have ever dealt with this, you know, nowadays and
if they really are concerned with this in a non-pagan world. You
know, like if somebody comes along and says, you know, the case
of the beam, somebody comes along and says yeah, I'm not using
my car anymore, I want to give it to, I want to
give it to היכל, Heichal, I want to give it to the
synagogue, you guys are so nice, right? Do we say oh wait,
did you mean to give it the Jewish way? Ha, so I
assume not. I assume that it's a lot less relevant in a
non-pagan world. Okay, let's go on. So now the גמרא Gemara says
like this, אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman
amar Rabbah bar Avuha, האומר סלע זו לצדקה, Ha-omer sela zu litzdaka,
did I skip a line? Oh, I skipped a line, I'm sorry.
לאו קדוש. Lav kadosh. דתניא, Detanya, how do you know?
היה כתוב על ידות הכלים, Haya kasuv al yedos hakelim, we have
a ברייתא braita, that says from מסכת סופרים, Masechet Sofrim, if God's
name was written על ידות הכלים al yedos hakelim on the handles
of vessels ועל כרעי המיטה ve-al kar'ei hamita or the legs of
a bed, הרי זה יגוד ויגנז, harei ze yagud ve-yiganez, you cut
out the place where God's name is and you bury it, but
it does not sanctify the whole vessel or the whole bed, only
the space that it's on. Fine. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר
אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha, האומר סלע זו לצדקה,
ha-omer sela zu litzdaka, this coin is for צדקה. tzedaka. Now we're
getting into a very important question now that we dealt with non-Jews
sanctifying, we're dealing with but it led us into a conversation of
donations. Now that we're talking about donations in synagogues, obviously a very
relevant conversation is not just to give to the synagogue but you
know, fund, you know,
like the appeals, raising money for צדקה, tzedaka, although I don't know
in the time of the גמרא, Gemara? I'm just sort of making
contemporary, I don't know if they did it in the context of
the synagogue. You know, they had these local institutions, communal institutions, such
as the קופה kuppa and the תמחוי, tamchui, גַבַּאי צְדָקָה, gabbai tzedaka,
I don't think it was sort of synagogue-based. But regardless, how do
you deal with צדקה? tzedaka? Is that like when you give something
to the temple, it becomes sanctified? If you set aside money for
צדקה, tzedaka, what status does that money have? And here's the question
that I'm sure has happened to all of us. We need change,
can we go ahead and take some change from our little צדקה
tzedaka box at home if we're going to pay back the money
later? Okay, so what?
Never even occurred to you.
Never even occurred to you. So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara So normally what you do is you actually exchange the
money, you put in a dollar bill and you take out some
change, and when I always do that I always take out less
change than the money I put in so I'm also giving a
little bit to צדקה. tzedaka. But let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara Okay. האומר סלע זו
לצדקה, Ha-omer sela zu litzdaka, this coin is for צדקה. tzedaka. What
is the status of the coin? מותר לשנותה. Mutar lishnosah. You can
actually switch it, meaning I'll use, forget it, I'm using this coin
to buy milk, I'll give another coin later. Okay, so it doesn't
have to be the exact coin. Right, obviously, but you can, it
doesn't become sanctified, you can use it for something else, you have
an obligation to give the money to צדקה tzedaka but it doesn't
have to be this coin. סבר מינה לעצמו אין לאחר לא. Savar
minah le'atzmo in le'acher lo. He thought,
we thought that what that meant was maybe you can use it
for yourself yes, for another no. but you can't actually like lend
the money to somebody else. It's not exactly clear once it's not
sanctified why there would have why we would have thought that difference,
but anyway,
because you know רשי Rashi says maybe we would have thought that
you always in your mind would have had a reservation, you know
wanted to have given yourself the option to use it but you
never would have thought to have reserved it for somebody else to
use. Anyway we thought to limit it that way, so אתמר אמר
רבי אמי אמר רבי יוחנן בין לעצמו בין לאחר. Itmar amar Rabbi
Ami amar Rabbi Yochanan bein la'atzmo bein la'acher. Doesn't matter whether you
or somebody else, the basic principle is you haven't sanctified the money.
And since you haven't sanctified the money, therefore you have to give
the money to צדקה, tzedakah, but you can use it, you can
lend it as long as you give the money. He said זו
סלע זו לצדקה. Zu sela zo l'tzedakah. Yeah, and you still haven't
sanctified the money. Oops. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay, okay, בין
לאחר. bein la'acher. אמר רבי זירא לא שנו אלא
דאמר עלי. Amar Rabbi Zeira lo shanu ela d'amar alai.
Now the גמרא Gemara wants to limit it. One minute, you're saying
you're not sanctifying the money? I'm not so sure about that. If
you said I have to give money to צדקה, tzedakah, then maybe
then you don't sanctify, maybe there even if he separates the money
afterwards as long as you haven't explicitly sanctified the money, as long
as you fundamentally is your obligation. Okay, but if you say אבל
אמר הרי זו, aval amar harei zu, בעינא
למיסב. be'ina l'meisiv. If you say this, then you have to give
that coin. So מתקיף לה רבא, maskif lah Rava, Rava asks
אדרבה איפכא מסתברא. adrabba ipecha mistabra. The opposite makes sense. I don't
think the opposite makes sense, but okay let's see what Rava says.
אמר זו, Amar zo, if you say this coin, נשתמש בה, nishtamesh
bah, we should encourage you to use it. Why? כי היכי דליחייב
באחריותה, Ki heichi d'lichayev b'achrayusa, so that you'll be responsible for it.
Meaning what? If you say this coin and you haven't accepted a
personal obligation, what happens if the coin gets lost? You don't have
to give anything. So since the צדקה tzedakah might lose out if
the coin gets lost, it's better that you should use it and
owe the money to צדקה, tzedakah, then we'll know that צדקה tzedakah
will get the money. But if you just leave it as that
coin, then maybe it'll get lost. אבל אמר עלי, Aval amar alai,
if you say I have an obligation, לא, then you anyway are
going to be obligated, so maybe we should more limit you because
you're going to have to be obligated regardless. So there you go,
there's policy considerations. אלא לא שנא, Ella lo shna, really it doesn't
matter. So here the גמרא Gemara it's very important because the גמרא
Gemara is essentially this is a question of when you say this
money, specifically when you say I have to give צדקה, tzedakah, we
already know that that's a נדר, Neder there's an obligation to pay,
you know there's בל תאחר, bal t'acher, we'll see in a minute,
but when you say this money, does it create a type of
sanctity? Now it can't be real sanctity because if it's real sanctity
how would the poor people use it? How could you buy food
with it? But does it give it some type of status that
therefore cannot be changed. And this גמרא Gemara at least sounds like
it doesn't, you can borrow but you have to pay back, it
doesn't give it status. But the answer is still not so obvious.
The רמבם Rambam very famously says that צדקה tzedakah is like a
נדר, neder not only your personal obligation but the status of the
coins, there's an aspect of something like sanctifying it. So that question
of the status of the money once designated
is an ongoing issue, but at least the simple sense of this
is that it does not have a status. Let's keep on going,
against the גמרא? Gemara No, you have to see this is not
the only voice in the matter.
Let's keep on reading, Mordechai's point I don't know if that's what
the intent is, but the result is that you get this kind
of aura about צדקה tzedakah that it's untouchable. Right. Or that you
it's not so simple, it's like you know postal theft, right. Right,
you open an envelope, federal crime. And this is the same kind
of effect.
Right, so that's really the question, meaning if you said you couldn't
use it at all then clearly it would have that status. And
the גמרא Gemara says you can borrow it and pay back. How
do we understand that? Do we say that and this sort of
goes to the question about the רמבם Rambam who emphasizes that it
does have status, do we understand that it has status but you're
given a certain latitude but it's like you sort of say, it's
like you know okay you can sort of take a little money
out of the till as long as you pay back before anybody
sees, which really you know but here we're saying you're allowed to
do it, but still there's a sense of taking צדקה tzedakah money,
not that it didn't have any status. I think that's the way
we feel, like once the money's in the צדקה tzedakah box, right,
like this money has to go to צדקה, tzedakah, and it really
does have some status in terms of the money itself. And that's
exactly sort of the idea that the רמבם underscores, but then saying
so then how am I allowed to borrow it is a little
bit of a question, right? So that's so we will continue to
go on.
Generally speaking though when we talk about things that are given a
status, that status becomes permanent. Even by something that's going to be
consumed, תרומה or whatever else is going to be consumed, it never
loses its status as תרומה all the way along that line, whereas
צדקה tzedakah as soon as the עני ani has it in his
hand, it's no longer...
That's a very good point. So you're saying more than just that
it's going to be used for food or whatever, but it's that
it's not consumed like תרומה and that actually...
But there's things that can be פדיון, pidyon, right?
מעשר שני... Ma'aser sheni... Yeah, but do we really think that the
עני ani goes takes the money and he buys milk with it
and now the milk has צדקה tzedakah status and like מעשר שני?
ma'aser sheni? I understand, I mean, but I think Mordechai is right,
we don't take it that far. When we conceptualize the status, it's
that it has to go to the עני. ani. That's the way
we
feel. Anyway, that's exactly what this גמרא's Gemara working out. So let's
keep on going. Okay, תניא כוותיה דרבא, Tanya Kavatei DeRabba, we taught
like רבא. נדר צדקה ואין הקדש צדקה. Neder tzedakah ve'ein hekdesh tzedakah.
נדר neder is צדקה tzedakah but הקדש hekdesh isn't צדקה. tzedakah. What
does that mean? מאי קאמר? Mai ka'amar? What is that saying? לא
נדר ולא הקדש צדקה. Lo neder velo hekdesh tzedakah. A נדר neder
is צדקה tzedakah and הקדש hekdesh is צדקה. tzedakah. צדקה Tzedakah is
צדקה. tzedakah. And a נדר neder. is a נדר neder and הקדש
hekdesh is הקדש. hekdesh. אלא הכי קאמר, Ela hachi ka'amar, this is
what it means. צדקה הרי היא בבל תאחר, Tzedakah harei hi beval
teachair, meaning נדר זו היא צדקה neder zu hi tzedakah really means
צדקה tzedakah is a נדר. צדקה Tzedakah is like a vow and
the same way if you take a vow to bring a קרבן
korban and you don't bring it within שלוש רגלים shalosh regalim you
transgress בל תאחר. bal teachair. If you take a vow to give
צדקה, tzedakah, this is very important when people make appeals, you know,
they actually say they're going to give money at an appeal, that
laws of בל תאחר bal teachair apply. Now, when do- what exactly
constitutes a vow and if you say a hundred dollars when they're
going around, is that a נדר or not, that's a question we're
not going to get into that when we learn נדרים, Nedarim, maybe
we'll talk about that more. But צדקה tzedakah definitely a- you can
have- if you commit to give צדקה tzedakah it can be a
vow and then it's בבל תאחר. beval teachair. So it does have
the status of a vow. ואינו כהקדש, Ve'eino kehekdesh, but it's not
like הקדש. hekdesh. דאילו הקדש אסור להשתמש בו. De'ilu hekdesh assur lishhtamesh
bo. הקדש, Hekdesh, the sanctity of הקדש hekdesh is it's totally off-limits.
ואילו צדקה שרי להשתמש בה, Ve'ilu tzedakah shari lishhtamesh bah, צדקה tzedakah
you can use. So again, how do you read that? Do you
read that as it doesn't have a status at all or that
it does have a status but it is this unique status? As
Mordechai said, a status that only lasts till it's given, a status
that you're allowed to borrow and pay back because that's in the
best interest of the עניים aniyim as we just said, that way
you'll make sure that it gets to them eventually because it'll be
an outstanding debt. Okay, so maybe it's a status but a status
with a lot more latitude.
So, yes, what are you saying for the גמרא gemara then? You
saying it's not like the one that you gave it, then what
is it?
Or what's the case
the גמרא gemara is talking about? What do you mean what's the
case? No, you said it's not necessarily- what?
You set aside money for צדקה. tzedakah. Not necessarily for an appeal.
Right. אמר רב כהנא. Amar Rav Kahana. ורמינהו לשמעתא קמיה דרב זביד.
Urminehu lishmata kamei deRav Zevid. מנהרדעא. Minarda. אמרו אתון הכי מתניתו לה.
Amru atun hachi matnitu lah. You said- there was an initial statement
and then you had to work out whether it applied to you
or to others, הרי זו הרי עלי, harei zu harei alai, that
those were later commentaries. מתנן אנן הכי
מתנינא לה. Matnan anan hachi matnina lah. Here's how we tell the
version that we had it all set in from the outset. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה אמר רב. Amar Rav Nachman amar
Rabbah bar Avuha amar Rav. האומר סלע זו לצדקה מותר לשנותה בין
לעצמו בין לאחר בין אמר עלי בין אמר הרי זו. Ha'omer sela
zu letzedakah mutar lishnotah bein le'atzmo bein le'acher bein amar alai bein
amar harei zu. That very from the outset the statement said everything
was covered. Whether for you, whether for somebody else, whether you said
on me, whether you set aside the money, whatever you do, צדקה
tzedakah if it has the- whatever the status is, you're still allowed
to borrow it and to use it and to pay back.
But nothing about בל תאחר.
bal teachair. Right, that was another point. תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. סלע
זו לצדקה, Sela zu letzedakah, if you say this סלע sela for
צדקה, tzedakah, עד שלא באה ליד גבאי, ad shelo ba'ah leyad gabbai,
until it comes to the hands of the גבאים, gabbaim, those are
the people that would actually collect and distribute, מותר לשנותה, mutar lishnotah,
you can use it for some other purpose and pay it back.
ומשבאה ליד גבאי, umisheba'ah leyad gabbai, once it comes to their hands,
אסור לשנותה, assur lishnotah, you cannot. איני, Eini, is this really true?
והא רב
ינאי יזיף ופרע. Veha Rav Yannai yazif ufara. Didn't רב ינאי, Rav
Yannai, who was a גבאי, gabbai, borrow against the צדקה tzedakah money
or borrow the צדקה tzedakah money and pay it back when he
needed it for other uses? He would borrow it and that was
he was himself the גבאי. gabbai. So the גמרא gemara. says, שאני
רב ינאי דניחא להו לעניים. Shani Rav Yannai denicha lehu la'aniyim. The-
the poor actually want- it was good for him, for them, for
him to borrow the money. Why they weren't getting it if he
was borrowing the money? דכמה דמשהי, Dechama demashi, because if he would
delay getting it back, since it was his responsibility to make sure
the poor get fed, imagine the scenario, he has a thousand dollars,
he needs it to pay his rent. Okay, so he pays his
rent. But now, he's it's his responsibility to make sure the poor
have food and there's no money in the coffers. So what's he
going to do? So it says, מצי ומייתי להו, Matzi umaiti lehu,
he compels the people to give more money because the poor are
starving and he gets them more donations. So therefore, the more the
coffers are empty at a given time, the more he he actually
it ends up- what? It doesn't help the poor anymore.
Why doesn't help the poor? They get fed one million- either way,
but he got to pay his rent.
No, but then he pays back.
Oh, he has to pay back? Yeah, he has to pay
back.
So therefore, in the end, it forces- you know, it winds up
to leading to more collection of funds. Now, what's important about this
is again that we are factoring in policy considerations and that it's
what's in the best interest of the עניים, aniyim, which is interesting.
If it's about some status, why would we factor this? But I
think the best way to understand it is, why when it comes
to the hand of the יד הגבאי yad hagabbai can you not
change it? Because the גבאי gabbai represents the עניים. aniyim. And when
it comes into his hands, he acquires it for the עניים. aniyim.
Then it's really their money. If it's their money, if it has
just some status, the status might give you a certain latitude. But
if they own it, then you can't take it and use it,
you're taking somebody else's money. But then we could also say if
it's in their best interest and they would want you to, then
we could say that implicitly you do have that permission. So that's
how I think it's
best
to understand.
So what what do we end up saying about the בל תאחר?
Bal Ta'acher? We just kind of gloss.
It is בל תאחר. Bal Ta'acher. If you take a vow to
give צדקה, tzedakah, the only question is what constitutes a vow.
I'm saying, I'm... but is it or is it not out of
here?
It is. Yes. If somebody has a vow to give צדקה, tzedakah,
they they don't give it within three רגלים, regalim, they're over בל
תאחר. Bal Ta'acher.
So the yousit kol, he
says that's the question: when you agree to give a donation, does
it constitute a vow or not? I'm not giving you an answer
to that right now. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Okay. We taught: ישראל
שנתנדב מנורה או נר לבית הכנסת. Yisrael she-nitnadev menora o ner le-beit
haknesset. Okay, now we're moving from צדקה tzedakah back to temple donations.
So you gave a candelabrum or a נר ner and נר ner
is not a candle, it's like a, you know, what... Lampstand. Not
candlestick. No, no, no, when they had metal things they put oil
in, a lamp, a lamp, okay, a lamp to the בית הכנסת,
beit haknesset, אסור לשנותה, asur lishnotah, then you can't use it for
something else, meaning now it's not you, but the temple basically wants
to go ahead and sell this and use "Thank you very much,
we have more than enough candelabrums, we're going to sell this and
get something that we want," okay? So you're not allowed to do
it. They sanctified it presumably, it's like a קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf,
not a קדושת דמים. kedushat damim. Again, this is interesting, it's בית
הכנסת, beit haknesset, it's not בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash, So let's take
a look. סבר רבי חייא בר אבא למימר לא שנא לדבר רשות
ולא שנא לדבר מצווה. Savar Rabbi Hiyya bar Abba le-meimar, lo shna
le-dvar reshut lo shna le-dvar mitzvah. It doesn't matter whether they you
can't use it for anything else, whether a thing of sort of
of discretion or whether even a מצווה mitzvah purpose. אמר ליה רב
אמי הכי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rav Ami, hachi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, no no no, we don't go that far. לא שנא לדבר
רשות אבל לדבר מצווה מותר לשנותה. Lo shna le-dvar reshut, aval le-dvar
mitzvah mutar lishnotah. For מצווה mitzvah purpose you can you can use
it. So, you know, of course you would why else would a
שול shul be using it other than what would be a דבר
רשות dvar reshut for the שול? shul? I don't know, maybe you
wanted to use it, you know, for a, you know, for some
type of a men's club evening or something like that, right, a
קידוש kiddush with you know, of course if you call right,
a דבר מצווה dvar mitzvah is like Torah. Right.
You mean a מצווה mitzvah object is what you're saying as opposed
to... yeah, it's not so clear. Let's take a look. The גמרא
gemara says: ואמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן עובד כוכבים שנתנדב מנורה
או נר לבית הכנסת. Ve-amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan, oveid kokhavim
she-nitnadev menora o ner le-beit haknesset. Now we get back to the
non-Jew, we've come full circle. He gives something specific. Remember the concern
before about giving something specific to the בית המקדש? Now we're talking
about giving something specific to the בית הכנסת. beit haknesset. He gives
a lamp or or candelabrum. עד שלא נשתקע שם בעליה אסור לשנותה.
Ad she-lo nishtaka sheim ba'aleha, asur lishnotah. So this is quite interesting.
By the בית המקדש we said don't accept. Here we're implicitly saying
you did accept it. So now you've accepted this donation of the
non-Jew and you have, you know, you have John Paul's candelabrum in
your in your lobby. So as long as people remember it by
the name of the non-Jew, you can't go ahead and use it
for something else. משנשתקע שם בעליה מותר לשנותה, Mishenishtaka sheim ba'aleha, mutar
lishnotah, once however people forgot who donated it,
then you are able to sell it and you know put it
to some other use. Why? As we're going to see obviously because
you don't want somebody to complain, it's "where's my candelabrum?" So as
if people don't remember it to the point where it's interesting, the
owner probably will always remember but somehow if it loses that sense
of being identified with him, then it's not so bad, you're not
so concerned about policy considerations about using it, but as long as
it's identified with him, it would be an insult to use it
for something else. It's like you get the gift, you know, for
your wedding that you would never use from your aunt Faye or
whatever it is, and then you only bring it out when... 'cause
where's the... anyway, so okay, so okay.
The Goldberg Diamond...
The Goldberg Diamond.
No, you'll feel... anyway. One minute, so, one minute, so. גופא. Gufa.
Now
what are you reusing this thing for? אילימא לדבר רשות, Ilima le-dvar
reshut, if you're reusing it for something of discretion, מאי איריא עובד
כוכבים, mai irya oveid kokhavim, why are we giving the scenario of
a non-Jew?
אפילו ישראל נמי, afilu Yisrael nami, even a Jew, right, presumably it
means you have more latitude by a Jew, whatever, but anyway you're
not allowed to use anything, whether by a Jew or a non-Jew,
for דבר רשות dvar reshut if it was given to the to
the synagogue. אלא לדבר מצווה, Ela le-dvar mitzvah, so if we're talking
that you are using it for something else, presumably you're using it
for a מצווה mitzvah purpose. And there we say, טעמא, ta'ama, you're
only limited if it's a non-Jew. Why are you limited if it's
a non-Jew and when and when the name is still is still
remembered? דעובד כוכבים הוא דפיי, De-oveid kokhavim hu, depayei, because he's a
non-Jew, דפיי, depayei, he literally that means something like, I'm trying to
think of a... it sort of means he croaks, like not croaks,
dies, like he complains, okay? We're afraid that he's going to say,
"What happened to my menorah?" and he's going to complain. אבל ישראל
לא פיי, Aval Yisrael, lo payei, but a Jew, of course they
would never... hey, what
did I... they're always giving with a full heart and you and
you can go ahead and you sell it and... actually it's a
big, big issue for a שול shul because, you know, somebody gives,
let's say, donates, you know, I don't know what it is, you
know, an ארון aron or something like that, and now for the...
Can you never accept other donations? Can you let's say not even
for the same ארון? aron? Somebody now it's 20 years later and
you still have the plaque of who gave the ארון aron and
somebody wants to give you know $100,000 and a gorgeous new ארון,
aron, but the people are going to complain, I gave that ארון
aron 20 years ago, it still has my name on it. So
it's a real issue, okay? So it's interesting that the גמרא gemara
assumed that that's only for non-Jews. Anyway, but for Jews, oh, that's
of course not an issue. שפיר דמי. shappir dami. Then of course
you can reuse it even when the name is still identified. So
anyway, so what do you see? So you see that you are
even when we allowed you to reuse, we are only allowing you
to reuse, you know, for a, I'm sorry, that when we say
you, excuse me, the other way, you can't reuse, you can only,
that only means you can't reuse for דבר רשות. devar reshus. But
if somebody gives a donation to the בית המקדש, to the, to
the synagogue, even of a specific item, you are allowed, if you're
not concerned about them complaining, you are allowed to go ahead and
sell it and use it and, you know, use the money and
do something else with it.
Jews or non-Jews?
No, non-Jews, the גמרא is just saying you're more concerned about complaining.
So basically it started with the statement that, it started with the
statement that if somebody gives a donation of a specific thing to
the, to a synagogue, you cannot reuse it. But then the גמרא
said basically that only means you can't reuse it for a non,
non-מצוה purpose. But if you want to sell it and use it
in another way for a מצוה purpose, you're allowed. And we know
that because the only limitation we find is by a non-Jew in
a case where we're concerned that it's going to lead to complaints.
But if that weren't the issue, you are definitely allowed to, you
know, sell it and use the, and use it for a different
purpose. So let's take a look now at the גמרא and this
discussion.
Okay. שזריק, Shazrik, I don't even know how to pronounce the name,
טייע, Taya, שזריק Shazrik the merchant, who was a non-Jew, אידני שרגא
לבי כנישתא, idne shraga l'bei knishta, he donated a lamp to a
temple, to a synagogue, דרב יהודה, d'Rav Yehuda, Rav Yehuda's temple. שניה
רחבא, Shanya Rechava, Rechava decided to use it for some other purpose.
Okay, so, you know, whatever, he sold it, he whatever, he took
it out of the synagogue, used the funds for something, for some
other thing. דאיקפיד רבא, D'ikpid Rava, Rava was upset, he said, you're
not allowed to do that, he donated, you have to leave it
there. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say שניה רבא ואיקפיד רחבא, shanya
Rava v'ikpid Rechava, the reverse. Rava used it for something else and
Rechava got upset.
But you understand, we're talking about a lamp.
ואיכא דאמרי, V'ika d'amri, שניה חזנא
דפומבדיתא, shanya chazana d'Pumbedisa, that the, that the people who changed it
were the חזנים, chazanim, meaning the synagogue officials, you know. דאיקפיד רחבא
ואיקפיד רבא, D'ikpid Rechava v'ikpid Rava, and both Rechava and Rava got
upset. Fine. Now, מאן דשניה סבר דלא שכיח, Man d'shanya savar d'lo
shechiach, the one who switched said, I know we're not supposed to
change things that non-Jews gave, but how likely is it that he's
going to drop by? He's a merchant, he's only here very infrequently.
So big deal, he almost is never here. ומאן דאיקפיד, U'man d'ikpid,
the one who got upset, סבר זימנין דמיקלע ואתי, savar zimnin d'mikla
v'asi, sometimes he does drop by, so you gotta have it, you
know, so at least if so, so, so you can't change it
even if he's not always here. So it's very interesting because as
opposed to the beginning of the סוגיא sugya which said, don't accept
a specific item that's labeled as a non-Jew, here it actually says
you can, and because it has that label, you have to be
concerned about what if, about policy considerations, about what if you want
to sell it and use it, you know, for some other purposes.
But basically we do have the principle that money given to צדקה
tzedakah can be reused, can be borrowed, borrowed and paid back until
it comes to the hands of the גבאי, gabbai, but it seems
like it still has the status of צדקה. tzedakah. And something given
to a synagogue, as opposed to given to a בית המקדש, which
is sanctified, also does not have real, you know, the same type
of sanctity and also can be sold and the funds used in
other ways. Okay. That was a really fascinating, relevant subject. We have
ten minutes to try to get a little further now in the
next משנה. Let's take a look. הגוסס והיוצא ליהרג, HaGoses v'Hayotzei L'Heireig,
somebody that is basically on his deathbed, you know, how גוסס goses
is defined is very important for medical ethics, ethics issue. But anyway,
somebody who is literally about to die,
what would we call it? Not critical, what's it called?
Terminal, thank you. והיוצא ליהרג, V'Hayotzei L'Heireig, and somebody that is actually
going to be executed. לא נידר ולא נערך, Lo nidar v'lo ne'erach,
they cannot, you cannot, if you say the value of that person,
they cannot be the object of a vow because they have no
market value, right? If sold as a slave, it would be zero.
Now the חידוש is also לא נערך, lo ne'erach, because that is
still a man or woman on this chart, so old, so old,
whatever, who cares if they don't have a market value. So let's
take a look. רבי חנינא בן עקביא אומר נערך, Rabbi Chanina ben
Akiva omer ne'erach, no, they are נערך, ne'erach, who cares that they
have no value, no, you know, market value? מפני שדמיו קצובים, mipnei
shedamav ketzuvim, it's a fixed value based on age and gender. רבי
יוסי אומר נודר ומעריך, Rabbi Yosi omer noder u'ma'arich, which wasn't really
debated, they can make a vow and they can obligate themselves in
ערך, erech meaning it's not supposed to be the object of the
vow or the ערך. ומקדיש, U'makdish, and they can sanctify items. ואם
הזיק חייב, V'im hizik chayav, and if they damage, they have to
pay. They're still subjects as it were, they're not objects. They as
an object of the vow, they have no market value and so
on, but they can still do things that are legally binding, make
vows, sanctify, pay for damages, and so on. We'll see what
that's
about.
So he's not arguing or supporting the position?
Right, although the גמרא that's what the גמרא is going to ask:
who is arguing about that? So let's take a look at the
גמרא. Okay, let's take a look where we're going to get, we
have four minutes, we're going to get to the two dots. No
talk.
בשלמא גוסס, bishlama goses, I understand the guy on the deathbed, לא
נידר, lo nidar, he's not an object of a vow, דלאו בר
דמים הוא, delav bar damim hu, he has no market value, ולא
נערך, velo neerach, he cannot be an object of an ערך, דלאו
בר העמדה והערכה הוא, delav bar haamada vehaeracha hu, if you remember
in the beginning of the מסכת masechet we quoted a verse that
they have to be able to be stood up, so since he
can't stand, therefore it's a technical exclusion. אלא יוצא ליהרג, ela yotze
lehareg, somebody who's about to be executed, בשלמא לא נידר, bishlama lo
nidar, I understand he's not the object of a vow, דלאו בר
דמים הוא, delav bar damim hu, no market value. אלא לא נערך
אמאי לא, ela lo neerach amai lo, why is he not an
ערך? דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא, braita, so the answer is,
דתניא, detanya, we taught a ברייתא, here's the reason. מניין ליוצא ליהרג,
minayin leyotze lehareg, how do you know that somebody who's about to
be executed, we're assuming it means executed by a Jewish court, ואמר
ערכי עלי, ve'amar erki alai, I accept upon myself to pay my
own ערך, or doesn't really matter if somebody else says he pays
the ערך, שלא אמר כלום, shelo amar klum, how do we know
it's not binding? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar כל חרם לא יפדה, kol
cherem lo yipadeh, anything that is חרם cherem shall not be redeemed,
which is being read to mean anything that is banned, that is
going to be destroyed, cannot be redeemed, and since the idea of
a vow, an ערך is like you're paying, it's conceptually somewhat like
a redemption, therefore we understand this to mean that there is no
ערך for somebody who is going to be executed. יכול אפילו קודם
שנגמר דינו, yachol afilu kodem shenigmar dino, maybe this would apply to
even before the בית דין beit din has given him the final
judgment that he will be executed? תלמוד לומר talmud lomar the verse
teaches מן האדם, min ha'adam, from people, דלא כל האדם, delo kol
ha'adam, not all people. So only once his final judgment, then is
there no ערך for him. ורבי חנינא בן עקביא, verabi chanina ben
akavya, the גמרא says, דאמר נערך, de'amar neerach, how about Rabbi Chanina
ben Akavya in the משנה that says he is נערך? neerach? That
doesn't buy into this whole דרשה. drasha. He just says he's a
person, he's got a value on the chart. האי כל חרם מאי
עביד ליה, hai kol cherem mai avid leh,
what does he do with this verse?
That's not a stupid question, there's no way the פשט pshat of
that verse would necessarily compel us to read it that way. So
the גמרא says fine, we have another דרשה drasha for that verse.
וכדתניא, ukedatanya, what does he do? וכדתניא, ukedatanya, like we taught, רבי
ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה אומר, rabi yishmael beno shel
rabi yochanan ben beroka omer, לפי שמצינו למיתות בידי שמיים שנותנין ממון
ומתכפר להם, lefi shematzinu lemitot bidei shamayim shenotnin mamon umitkafer lahem, since
we know that sometimes people who are deserving of heavenly death can
give a כופר kofer money for atonement, שנאמר, shenemar, the verse says,
אם כופר יושת עליו, im kofer yushat alav, that if a person's
ox gores and kills somebody, he pays atonement money, so therefore we
see something that you could be deserving in some virtual way of
death and pay atonement money. So therefore once we've introduced the concept
of atonement money, יכול אף בידי אדם כן, yachol af bidei adam
ken, maybe you can even pay atonement money if you're deserving of
a death in the court, of an execution? תלמוד לומר, talmud lomar,
yes, כל חרם לא יפדה, kol cherem lo yipadeh, anything that is
banned, meaning again reading it like a person that is going to
be executed, cannot be redeemed, but it's a much better read of
not redeemed, meaning you can't pay money to save him from the
execution,
no כופר kofer money. אין לי אלא מיתות חמורות שלא ניתנה שגגתן
לכפרה, ein li ela mitot chamurot shelo nitna shegagatan lechapara, maybe that's
only the heavy death that there is that you would never have
any atonement with them, meaning that if you did them בשוגג beshogeg
you would not be able to bring a קרבן, korban, there are
some things that there's no קרבן korban for if he does it
בשוגג, beshogeg, רש"י rashi says specifically things like blasphemy, okay, but really
the reason there's no קרבן korban is because it's not an action,
it's only verbal, but anyway, maybe this is only types of executions
that never have a concept of atonement with them even if they're
done
בשוגג? beshogeg? מיתות קלות שניתנה שגגתן לכפרה, mitot kalot shenitna shegagatan lechapara,
things that when they're done, when they're done unintentionally,
not willfully, that there is atonement, maybe there you would be able
to pay money to atone because there's a concept of atonement? תלמוד
לומר, talmud lomar, כל חרם, kol cherem, anything under the ban. So
in the end there's not a real good reason why a person
does not have an ערך, it's only a question of do you
learn it from the verse, and the one that says he does
have an ערך says the verse is telling you what I would
assume is much more the פשט pshat of the verse that means
that or closer to the פשט pshat that if a person is
going to be executed he cannot redeem himself, they cannot pay any
כופר kofer money. Okay, we will end here.
It's interesting that you
say that about